海貍
這就是沃特·布萊克
This is a picture of Walter Black,
一個陷入絕望的抑鬱癥患者
a hopelessly depressed individual.
而在他內心某處 住著一個曾經墜入愛河
Somewhere inside him is a man who fell in love,
組建起美滿家庭
who started a family...
接著我醒了
And then I woke up.
...事業有成的人
...who ran a successful company.
但這個人卻已經消失不見了
That man has gone missing.
不管他怎樣努力
No matter what he's tried,
用盡一切辦法
and he's tried everything,
沃特對他的離去卻束手無策
Walter can't seem to bring him back.
就好像他實際上已經死了
It's as if he's died
卻沒能帶上他的肉體一起離開
but hasn't had the good sense to take his body with him.
所以大部分的時間他都用來睡覺
So, mostly, what he does is sleep.
他父親曾經引以為傲的玩具公司的股份
Shares in his father's once-proud toy company
如今卻和沃特的感受一樣 變得一文不值
are now almost as worthless as Walter feels.
他那好像節日賀卡一樣美滿幸福的家庭
His family used to resemble something out of a holiday greeting card
現在卻充滿了無休止的哀傷
but now seems to be in perpetual mourning.
他最小的孩子亨利已經成為老師口中的"獨行俠"
Henry, his youngest, has become what his teachers call "solitary. "
總有一天他會成為隱形人
He'd like to become invisible one day
而不僅僅是被他親生父親忽視
instead of merely unnoticed by his own father.
而珀特 他的大兒子
And, Porter, his eldest?
害怕會變得像他父親那樣
Well, he's terrified of becoming just like his father.
他的任務? 就是記錄他倆之間每個可怕的相似點
His mission? To catalog every dreaded similarity that links them.
每一次咬嘴唇
Every lip bite.
每一次把脖子弄得吱嘎響 每一次無意識的行為
Every neck crack. Every involuntary behavior.
他決心一個一個地將它們抹去
He plans to erase them one by one.
妻子梅勒迪斯埋首於她的工程事務
His wife, Meredith, has hidden herself behind her engineering work
晚上與東京的電話會議 以及雲霄飛車的設計工作
and nighttime conference calls to Tokyo and roller coaster designs.
任何能讓她擺脫丈夫不在身邊 這一事實的事
Anything to drown out the reality of an absent husband.
沃特的抑鬱癥就像一滴墨汁
Walter's depression is an ink
影響著所有他遇到的事
that stains everything it touches.
像一個黑洞 吞噬他身邊所有的人
A black hole that swallows all who get near.
他們都在等待著他醒過來
They've all been waiting for him to wake up,
重新振作起來
to snap out of it,
但他遲遲不見好轉
but he hasn't.
所以 梅勒迪斯做了最後唯一能做的
So, Meredith does the only thing left to do
說了最後唯一能說的
and says the only thing left to say.
再見
Goodbye.
賈裡德 你這科都要掛了
Jared, you're failing this class.
你真覺得你突然交出一份滿分的論文
Do you honestly think you can suddenly hand in an "A" paper
你能逃之夭夭?
and get away with it?
那赫克托呢?
What about Hector?
你幫他在家庭發展上拿到了A
You got him an "A" in Family Development.
聽著 我從來沒有幫赫克托寫過東西 明白了嗎?
Look, I've never written anything for Hector. All right?
如果他是那麼和你說的 他就是個騙子
If he told you differently, he's a liar.
想想 即使我真幫他寫了論文
Hypothetically, had I written him something,
就得繼續不斷把他的分數提高
we would have raised his grades incrementally.
如果真是這樣 那麼他最後才會拿到A
And if that happened, then, yes, he might have turned in an "A" paper.
在他經常掛掉的課上 拿到B就算不錯了
He might even be making a "B" in a class that he used to be failing.
所以 要是有人想讓我幫忙
So, if someone wanted me to do this,
那就得照著他們的樣子辦事
and do it as them,
以他們的口吻 在他們的能力之內
in their voice and at their skill level,
我會告訴他們要不按我說的辦
I would say that they could either do it my way
要不試試你的運氣 從網上買幾篇廢紙
or take your chances buying some piece of shit off the Internet.
每次200?      要是嫌多就自己寫去
$200 every time?        If it's too much, write it yourself.
比大麻還貴
More than I pay for weed.
(體育館 明天4點)
對不起 孩子
Sorry, buddy.
你又沒看到我
You passed me again.
我知道 寶貝 我那是在找你啊
I know, honey. I was looking.
今天怎麼樣?
How was your day?
和別人說話了嗎?
Did you talk to anyone?
我想是的
I guess.
新朋友還是老朋友?
A new person or an old person?
新的
New.
很好 你們都說了什麼呢?
Good. What did you talk about?
他說我是慫蛋
He said I was a ball-licker.
我說我不是 他就把我扔進垃圾箱裡了
I told him I wasn't, and he threw me in the dumpster.
什麼
What?
你告訴老師了嗎?
Did you tell your teacher?
是她把我從垃圾箱裡弄出來的
She got me out of the dumpster.
這肯定有些誤會
Well, this must be some kind of misunderstanding,
我們必須要調解糾正他們的...
and we just have to realign or correct their...
我會和老師談談
I'll talk to the teacher.
爸爸走了?
Is Dad gone?
不 他沒離開 寶貝
No. He's not gone, honey.
只是我們都覺得不在一起生活比較好
We just agreed that it's better if we don't live together anymore.
知道嗎?
Okay?
你想在海的另一邊尋找什麼 孩子
What do you look for beyond the sea, Grasshopper?
知之甚少的那部分自我
That part of me which I know little of.
我的前世
The past of which I was born.
那麼有一天 你會找到它的
Then, some day, you must seek it.
尋求過去是對的嗎? 波大師
Is it good to seek the past, Master Po?
它不會擾亂現在嗎?
Does it not rob the present?
如果一個人總是沉溺在過去 他就會毀掉現在
If a man dwells on the past, then he robs the present.
但是如果忽視過去 那麼他則會毀掉未來
But if a man ignores the past, he may rob the future.
命運的種子需要細心呵護
The seeds of our destiny are nurtured...
這就是它們的美好之處 孩子
That's beautiful, Grasshopper.
來 喝酒
Here. Here you go.
你不喝
You moved.
嘿!
Oi!
你知道 既然我們現在正做些改變
You know, since we're making changes around here,
也許你需要請個水管工之類的
maybe you want to get, like, a plumber or something.
我是說這地方都快塌了
I mean, this place is falling apart.
那實在太糟了
Well, that's too bad,
我們對此實在沒什麼辦法 不是嗎?
because there's really not much we can do about it, is there?
哇哦 放鬆點 我站在你這邊
Whoa, relax. I'm on your side, okay.
我很高興你把他踢出去了
I'm glad you kicked him out.
這只是餐桌上的討論而已
I'm just saying this whole eating-at-the-table thing together.
我的意思是 你打算讓他在外面多久?
I mean, that's... How long do you expect us to keep that up?
不知道 珀特
I don't know, Porter.
也許等到我們重新學會相互尊重?
Maybe until we start respecting each other again?
也許等到我們開始關心對方今天過得怎麼樣
You know, maybe when we start asking each other how was our day
把盤子清理乾淨的時候
and clearing out the dishes...
也許我也該制定一張路線圖
Maybe I should get a paper route, too.
接著 我要猜這個數字
Then I'm going to guess the number.
如果我才對了 我們就開始小貓咪的故事
If I guess right, we do the kitten story.
今晚有兩個故事 實在太頭疼了
Two big stories to get to tonight, unfortunately...
醒醒
Wake up.
起來 你個沒用的笨蛋
Wake up, you worthless sod.
天吶 瞧瞧你的樣子
Bloody hell. Look at you.
醉得不省人事 被電視機壓在下面
Stone-drunk and flattened by a television.
你真是在給自己寫訃告啊 沃特
That's quite an obituary you're working up for yourself, Walter.
走開
Leave me alone.
不不不不 我才不要走 你不想我走開的
No. Can't do that. You don't want that.
因為我是唯一一個真正瞭解你內心感受的人
'Cause I'm the only one what knows how you really feel.
人人都需要個朋友 沃特
Everybody needs a friend, Walter.
我就是你的朋友
And you've got me.
就是因為這你把那些自我救贖的書讀了個遍
That's why you read all them useless self-help books.
什麼《心情雞湯》《正向思考》《友情秘訣》
Chicken Soup, Positive Thinking, How to Win Friends.
哪本書教你把電視往自己腦袋上砸的?
Which one has the chapter about dropping the telly on your head?
我病了
I'm sick.
的確 沃特 這點我們達成共識
Yeah, Walt. On that, we agree.
問題是 你想不想好起來?
The question is, do you want to get better?
我做不到
I can't.
是啊是啊是啊 你得了抑鬱癥 哦 是啊
Yeah, yeah, yeah. You're depressed. Yeah.
昏昏沉沉 鬱鬱寡歡
Lethargic. Anhedonia.
醒醒吧!
Wake up!
那些書還有小藥片 那都是些棉花糖
Books and pills. They're cotton candy.
你看太多家居裝飾的節目
You've seen too many home-improvement shows.
以至於你真覺得僅僅靠
You think you can just
重新刷個漆 重新挪一下家俱的位置
splash up some paint and rearrange the furniture,
接著所有的一切都會恢復正常
and everything will be all right.
你想不想做些改變? 我是說 真正的改變?
You want things to change? I mean, really change?
你要忘了那些家居裝潢的想法 沃特
You gotta forget about home improvement, Walter.
你該去把這該死的房子炸掉
You have gotta blow up the whole bloody building.
那麼你要怎麼做呢? 沃特
What are you gonna do, Walter?
炸了它      大聲點!
Blow it up.        Louder!
炸了它! 把他媽的炸了! 炸了它! 炸了它!
Blow it up! Blow it the fuck up! Blow it up! Blow it up!
很好
Right.
太對了 夥計
Too right, mate.
你可以把它都炸了 再重新開始
You can blow it up. Start again.
你是誰?
Who are you?
我是海貍先生 我為拯救你那苦逼的生活而來
I'm the Beaver, Walter, and I'm here to save your goddamn life.
嗨
Hey.
抱歉 我一定又錯過他了 他擠進人群裡了
I'm sorry. I must have passed him again. He just blends in.
不 他父親早就把他接走了
No, his dad picked him up early.
沃特?
Walter?
他說他給你發了短信 你丈夫真是個與眾不同的人
He said he sent you a text. Your husband is quite a character.
媽媽 你真該來看看我們的傑作
Mom, you gotta see what we did.
好啊 你爸爸呢?      快來 我給你看
Okay. Where's your father?        Come on! I'll show you.
你把回憶存在裡面
You put your memory in it.
你從哪找到的?
Where'd you get that?
這是我們做的      你和你爸爸?
We made it.        You and your dad?
我和海貍先生
Me and the Beaver.
海貍先生?
The Beaver?
知道沃特把磨石機塞哪了嗎?
Any idea where Walter stuffed the power sander
兩年前你送他的那個聖誕禮物
you gave him two Christmases ago?
不知道?
No?
沒關係 我們能應付
No trouble. We'll make do.
沃特 那個口音和玩偶是怎麼回事?
Walter, what's with the accent and the puppet?
把東西給她      好
Give her the thing.        Right.
"你好 給你這張名片的人
"Hello. The person who handed you this card
"現在正處於一隻治癒玩偶的照顧中"
"is under the care of a prescription puppet. "
沃特 這到底是怎麼回事?
Walter, what the hell is this?
亨利 你去看看能不能找到我們剛才說的清漆
Henry, mate, go see if you can find that varnish we was talking about.
我會找到的!      謝謝 夥計!
I'll get it!        Thanks, mate!
你看完名片了?
Did you read the card?
是的 我...      看名片
Yes, I...         Read the card.
我已經...      看名片
I've...         Read the card.
"你好 給你這張名片的人
"The person who handed you this card
"現在正處於一隻治癒玩偶的照顧中
"is under the care of a prescription puppet
"目的是為了在他自身和消極人格之間
"designed to help create a psychological distance between himself
"創造一個心理隔斷
"and the negative aspects of his personality.
"請你像正常一樣對他
"Please treat him as you normally would
"但是把注意力集中到玩偶身上 謝謝"
"but address yourself to the puppet. Thank you. "
就是這樣
There you go.
這是什麼玩笑麼?
Is this some kind of a joke?
不 親愛的 這可不是什麼玩笑
No, hardly, love. Nothing funny about it.
別再擺弄那玩偶了!
Stop it with the puppet!
好吧 我很迷惑 沃特 我需要解釋 就現在
All right. I'm confused, Walter, and I need some answers right now.
他說如果我堅持這麼做 也許...
He said if I stick with it that maybe...
他? 誰說的?
He? Who said that?
梅西醫生
Dr. Macy.
梅西醫生? 你早就不去看他了
Dr. Macy? You quit seeing him.
好吧 我又回去了
Well, I went back.
那麼這算是某種康復療程?
So this is some kind of a program?
讓我來說 是的 梅勒迪斯 答案是 是的
I'll field that one. Yes, Meredith. The answer is yes.
就是這樣
That is exactly what it is.
我知道儘管這聽上去有點荒唐
I know it seems radical,
但是在沃特這種病例上
but in cases like Walter's,
在這種其他方法都不起作用的病例上
cases where all else has been known to fail,
看得出來 它很有效果
it's proven quite effective.
但是想要他起作用 就需要你的全力支持
But if it's going to work, it's going to need your full support.
這在瑞典很流行
It's very big in Sweden.
我找不到
I couldn't find it.
啊 別擔心
Ah. No worries.
我還是自己找吧
I best be on me boy.
你不會離開 對吧?
You're not leaving, are you?
不用擔心 週末我會再回來
Don't worry. I'll come back this weekend, then.
但是你得留下來吃飯! 媽媽 讓他留下來吃飯吧!
But you have to stay for dinner! Mom, let him stay for dinner!
好吧 沒事
Look, it's all right.
我不需要      求你了 媽媽 讓他留下吃飯吧
I don't need to.        Please, Mom, let him stay for dinner.
我下個週末還會來的      拜託了
I'll come back this weekend, then.        Come on.
只是吃個飯 沒問題      求你了 媽媽
It's okay. Just for dinner.        Please, Mom.
耶!      那麼 好吧
Yeah!        Well, right, then.
讓我們把車庫整理一下 好讓我們去廚房搗亂
Let's tidy up the garage so we can mess up the kitchen.
來吧 不要碰鋒利的東西
Come on. Don't touch anything sharp.
嗨
Hey.
你找我來幹什麼?
What the hell am I doing here?
我需要你幫我寫點東西
I need you to write me something.
我早就知道 他以為我會跳進這個圈套?
I knew it. He thinks I'm going to fall for this?
誰?      默菲 或是別的
Who?        Mumphry, or whatever
副校長讓你來的
vice-principal sent you.
告訴他這是在侮辱我
Tell him I'm insulted.
嘿 你能不能等一下? 沒人派我來
Hey, will you hold on for a second? No one sent me.
我真的很需要幫助
I really need help.
聽著 你是畢業典禮的致辭人 好不好 績點4分
Look, you're the valedictorian, all right. You have a 4.0.
我還需要抄你的微積分答案
I copy off of you in calculus.
為什麼你還要我幫你寫論文?
Why would you want me to write you a paper?
不是論文
It's not a paper.
是我的畢業演講
It's my graduation speech.
省省吧 沒人會在乎那些事
Save your money. No one gives a shit about those things.
好吧 但是我媽媽會 所以...
Yeah, well, my mom will. So...
我不是在說你當槍手幫別人寫論文
Not that I'm saying that you write other people's papers for them,
但如果真是你做的
but if you did,
我聽說你很擅長模仿他們口吻
I hear that you're really good at making yourself sound like them.
瞭解他們的想法 這就是我需要的
Getting inside their heads. That's what I need.
不行      為什麼?
No way.        Why?
對你那些厭食的拉拉隊友來說
Because it's one thing for your little anorexia squad
光看長相就能看透她們
to get by on their looks.
他們也就這點能耐了
That's all they've got.
但對於你這樣的人來說 根本就是自己懶得干
But for someone like you, it's just lazy.
站在
Hold on.
等等
Wait a minute.
這對你來說是因為懶得幹麼?
Does this look lazy to you?
懶得看那428頁
That is 428 pages of lazy.
如果不想收錢替我幹活
And if you don't want to take my money
是因為等不及想看到我
because you're just dying to see me
出醜的樣子 那麼算了
make an ass of myself, then that's fine.
但是不許罵我懶骨頭
But don't you dare call me lazy.
蠢貨
Douche.
謝謝 想要在你的沙拉裡來點橄欖麼?
Thank you very much. You want olives in your salad?
好的      給 看著
Yeah.        Here you go. Watch this.
還要麼?
Would you like some more?
這是...      他回來了 你好
What the...        There he is. Hello.
我的名片
My card.
很抱歉 你回來之前我們就開始了
We was afraid we'd have to start without you.
這是開玩笑吧 啊?
This is a joke, right?
不 孩子 這是個全新的開始
No, son, it's a fresh start.
你是瘋了嗎?
Have you completely lost your mind?
我知道這有點...      我沒問你 瘋子
I know it seems a bit...        I'm not talking to you, nut job.
我在和媽媽說話
I'm talking to Mom.
你花了幾年時間才把他從這踢出去
It takes you years to get him out of here,
結果第二天你就放他進來了
and you let him come back the next night
還帶著個說話的玩偶?
with a talking hamster?
這種大公司在一夜之間倒閉是不可能的事
Failure on this scale doesn't happen overnight.
我還是不相信你們倆做了這個
Still I can't believe that you guys made that.
我是說 你從來...我的意思是 沃特從來...
I mean, you never... I mean, Walter never...
抱歉 我還並不是很明白我該怎麼和你講話
I'm sorry. I'm not quite sure how I'm supposed to address you.
噢 你幹得不錯 親愛的
Well, you're doing fine, love.
工具總是出現在你的聖誕採購單上
Well, tools were always on your Christmas list,
但我不知道你竟然知道怎麼做東西
but I had no idea that you knew how to actually make anything.
他是只海貍 媽媽 他們天生就是幹這個的
He's a beaver, Mom. That's what they do.
噢 完全正確 夥計
Yeah. Spot on, mate.
但是你知道 沃特曾經的手藝也不懶
But, you know, Walter wasn't half-bad himself, at one time.
是嗎? 誰教他的?
Yeah? Who taught him?
我猜他自學成才
I suppose he taught himself.
他還像你這麼大的時候 小童子軍
He was about your age, yeah. Cub Scouts.
他本打算和他爸爸一起造一輛賽車去參加比賽
He and his pop were supposed to make a race car for a contest.
但是 他爸爸不在 所以他只能自己干
Except, his pop weren't around so he had to do it himself.
他爸爸去哪了?
Where was his dad?
他十分傷心 後來就出了一場車禍
He got very sad and he had an accident.
你是說躺在墓地裡的傑瑞爺爺?
You mean Grandpa Jerry from the graveyard?
對 不管怎麼樣 沃特擁有了爺爺的工具
Right-o. Anyway, Walter had Grandpa's tools
但是不知道如何使用
but no clue how to use them.
所以 他最後做出的成果很糟糕
So, what he ended up making was so awful
看上去就好像他把一套輪胎
that it looked like he'd screwed a set of wheels
裝在了一堆狗屎上
onto a piece of dog crap.
你知道其他孩子怎麼叫它的嗎?
And you know what the other kids called it?
糞球 那還算好的了 夥計
The Turd. That was generous, mate.
有位女士因為它靠得太近了而大吐特吐
One lady threw up all over herself just 'cause it got close to her.
但是當他駛向比賽場...
But when it came to racing...
怎麼了?
What?
糞球所向匹敵 無人能擋
The Turd could not be beat.
太牛了      是啊
Sweet.        Yeah.
老爸?      怎麼了 夥計?
Dad?        Yeah, mate?
我們能造一個糞球麼?      當然 隨時可以
Can we make a Turd?        Yeah, anytime, mate.
你把它的樣子告訴我 我們就可造糞球了
You give the word, we'll make the Turd.
嗯
Yeah.
晚安 海貍先生
Good night, Beaver.
晚安 夥計
Good night, mate.
晚安
Good night.
晚安 海貍先生
Good night, Beaver.
喂?      諾拉
Hello?        Norah.
嘿 我是珀特
Hey, it's Porter.
聽著 之前我說的那些話...
Listen, what I said earlier...
那麼你到底要不要幫我?      當然
So, are you going to help me or not?        Yeah.
但是對這種事
But for this sort of thing,
我得開價大概500塊?
I'm going to have to ask you for, like, $500?
成交
Done.
哇哦 1000塊你也成交嗎?
Wow. Would you have gone $1,000?
噢 當然      一百萬呢?
Oh, yeah.        How about a million?
你明天能過來一趟嗎?
Can you come by tomorrow?
好好好 那當然
Yeah! Yeah, yeah, yeah. Absolutely.
我沒有...聽著 我...我們沒什麼交情 不是嗎?
You know, I didn't... Look, I... We're cool, right? I... I'm...
你從來都沒和我說過一個字 你知道 而且...
You've never even said a word to me, you know, and...
珀特?      而且我們也不像...
Porter?        And it's not like we
很瞭解對方還是什麼的...嗯?      明天過來
know each other or anything... Yeah.        Just come by tomorrow.
好吧      就這麼定了
Okay.        Okay.
晚安! 明天見
Good night! See you soon.
相信我 夥計 今天我們要還你自由
Trust me, mate. Today will set you free.
這究竟是什麼?
What the hell is this?
我不知道
I have no idea.
這是要裁員 不是嗎? 該死的中國
This is layoffs, isn't it? Goddamn China.
沒人會被辭退
Nobody's getting laid off.
好久不見?
Get rid of you lot?
我不能到處使喚人了 對嗎?
I'd have no one to boss around, yeah?
老闆清醒了 還帶了個朋友
The boss woke up and brought a friend.
我想我們得保持尊重 等布萊克先生告訴我們...
I think we should maintain some respect until Mr. Black tells us...
大家早上好
Good morning, all.
我想你們都拿到那些名片了
I assume you all got the cards.
如果沒有 請允許我簡單解釋一下
If not, allow me to briefly explain.
沃特·布萊克兩年前上任這家公司的CEO
Walter Black ascended to CEO of this company two years ago.
不是因為什麼特殊的才能或是優點
Not through any particular skill or merit,
只是沃特是繼承人
but because Walter was next in line
而不是站在那的資深副總
rather than our infinitely more qualified VP standing right here.
你好 親愛的
Hello, love.
沃特 嗯 還沒做好接手這工作的準備
It was a job Walter was, well, ill-prepared to handle.
基本上...
Basically, well...
沃特是個失敗者
Walter's been a loser.
這就是現在他退出 而讓我接手職位的原因
Which is why, as of now, he is resigning and putting me in charge.
那麼 在你們決定要把我扔到鐵軌上
So, before you decide to run me out on a rail
把我燒死之前
with all the flaming torches and pitchforks,
給我五分鐘 聽我把話講完
hear me out, give me five minutes,
之後要殺要剮悉聽尊便
then you may tear me to shreds, if you like.
首先 我將會取消對單個項目的管理
First, I will be ceding control of all individual projects
回到以前的團隊管理
back to the teams themselves.
也就是說你們自由了
That means you will be free
你們會回到一開始的本職工作
and entrusted to do the jobs you was hired to do in the first place.
你好 漢克
Hello, Hank.
其次 我們會重新整頓 恢復生氣 重新參展
Second, we will revamp, revitalize, re-launch
六周後的
at the International Game and Toy Manufacturers Expo
國際遊戲暨玩具廠商展覽會
in six weeks' time.
我明白你們對我的領導能力
Now, I know there's a very high degree of skepticism
有諸多質疑
about my ability to lead.
不是嗎?
Isn't that right?
一個中年老男人 他的手臂塞在我屁股裡
I mean, middle-aged man with his arm stuck up my bum. Right?
誰不會懷疑我呢? 不過我也會給你們以下選擇
Who wouldn't doubt me? But I'll make you the following deal.
給我兩周的時間 就兩周 兩周之後
You give me two weeks, just two, and at the end of that time,
任何人想要離開都會得到一筆豐厚的解雇賠償金
anyone who wants to resign will receive severance pay
還有一封漂亮的推薦信
and a glowing letter of recommendation.
一言為定 絕無例外      抱歉?
No questions asked, no exceptions.        Excuse me?
你到底是誰?
And who exactly are you supposed to be?
天吶 我忘記自我介紹了?
Bollocks. Did I forget to introduce myself?
你們可以叫我海貍先生
You may simply call me the Beaver.
太牛了
Impressive.
那麼 你需要瞭解什麼?
So, what do you need to know?
我想首先我得知道你要說些什麼?
Well, I guess the first thing is, what do you want to say?
這就是問題所在
Well, that's kind of the problem.
我是說 我的成績不錯 算是個人物 還有什麼?
I mean, I got good grades. Big deal. What do I know?
那你做這些事的時候你想別人怎麼看你?
Okay. Well, how do you want people to feel when you're done?
我覺得我只想著不要讓他們
I guess I just want them to feel not
失望
let down.
"不要失望"
"Not let down. "
這點很好
That's powerful.
"我很激動很興奮 你怎麼樣?"
"I'm excited, pumped. How are you doing?"
"我? 我從不讓人失望"
"Me? I'm not let down. "
我告訴過你我很挫的 所以我才需要你
I told you that I suck. This is why I need you.
好吧 你是啦啦隊長 出了名的急性子
Okay, well, you're a cheerleader, notorious hothead.
能說說你八年級是怎麼被開除的麼?
Could we talk about you getting expelled from the eighth grade?
你怎麼知道這事?
How did you find out about that?
有網絡無秘密
No secrets on the Internet.
你幹了什麼?
What did you do?
你偷了誰的百科全書?
Did you steal some encyclopedias?
吸煙?      不是
Chew some nicotine gum        No.
那是什麼? 嘲笑小胖墩?
What? Tease a fat kid?
住口
Shut up.
好吧 那麼究竟是什麼?
All right. So, what is it?
我正在標記
I was tagging.
標記?
Tagging?
就像...
Like...
像隨手塗鴉?
Like graffiti tagging?
更像是藝術創作 只是這是非法的
More like art. It was just illegal.
那現在那個叛逆的作品在哪?
Where's all this rebel-artist shit now?
很久之前的事了
That was a long time ago.
你還保留了一些 不是嗎?
You still have some, don't you? Yeah.
給我看看      不
Show me, please.        No.
如果你給我看
If you show me,
我就能寫出能讓你解放西藏的演講
I will write you a speech that you could free Tibet with.
為什麼你這麼想看?
Why do you want to see it so bad?
因為我想要驚喜
Because I like to be surprised.
我們得快點      好吧
We have to be quick.        All right.
這是誰的房間?
Whose room is this?
沒人住
No one's.
噢 天啊
Oh, wow.
我想畫張全景的
I like to do it big.
有高速公路 各種建築 廣告牌什麼的
Like freeways, buildings, billboards.
而且速度很快 好像我一小時能跑百萬英里
And fast. Like I'm running a million miles an hour.
不用費力去思考 你懂嗎?
No thinking, you know?
你為什麼放棄了?
Why did you stop?
因為我被逮到了 我媽媽受不了這個
'Cause I got caught and my mom couldn't take it.
不管怎樣 我把它們都扔了
Anyway, I threw them all away.
肯定有人喜歡他們
Someone must have liked them.
把它們從垃圾裡救回來 不是嗎?
Pulled them out of the trash, didn't they?
誰會那麼干呢?      你們在這幹嗎?
Who was it?        What are you doing in here?
我只是帶著珀特在屋裡轉轉
I was just showing Porter around the house.
我們在一個數學小組
He's on the math team with me.
好吧      時間不早了
Right.        Time to go.
對我媽的態度 我很抱歉
Hey, I'm sorry about my mom.
她只是 你知道...      沒事
She's just, you know...        That's fine.
你知道 你非常
You know, you are
非常奇怪
so much weirder...
不是奇怪 我的意思是 與眾不同
Not weird, I just mean, like, different, I guess.
你比我想像中更加獨特
You're a lot more different than I thought you'd be.
對於一個我出高價
You know, for someone I'm paying a lot of money
請他幫我寫演講稿的人來說
to write a speech for me,
你有點詞不達意
you're not very articulate.
我的文筆比口才好
I'm much better on paper.
我們拭目以待
We'll see.
謝謝你沒笑我
Thank you for not laughing, I guess.
我不會那麼干
I wouldn't do that.
我不會嘲笑你
I wouldn't laugh.
很好
Good.
非常好
Very, very good.
*記憶中我們相見在北海邊*
*We salute at the threshold of the North Sea in my mind*
*點點頭對著帶我來這的一堆煩心事*
*And a nod to the boredom that drove me here*
*面對潮水 開始游泳*
*To face the tide and swim*
*我游啊游啊*
*I swim, oh, swim*
接著最後看起來奇怪的事 變得司空見慣
And, eventually, what seems strange becomes common.
看起來不可能的事 變得無比真實
What seemed impossible becomes real.
*水已經沒過膝蓋 我該再等等 還是跳入水中?*
*Up to my knees now, do I wait? Do I dive?*
*大海似乎很瞭解我*
*The sea has seen my like before*
*雖然這是我第一次也是最後一次游泳*
*though it's my first and perhaps last time*
*請叫我施洗者 請稱這是一場洗禮*
*Let's call me a Baptist, call this the drowning of the past*
*她站在海邊 衝我背後扔石頭*
*She's there on the shoreline Throwing stones at my back*
*所以游泳吧 直到你見不到陸地*
*So swim until you can't see land*
*游吧 直到你見不到陸地*
*Swim until you can"t see land*
*你是個人還是個沙包?*
*Are you a man or are you a bag of sand?*
直到一切變得像以前一樣
Until things almost start to feel the way they used to.
修好了 親愛的 跟新的似的
Fixed it, love. Working like a charm.
好像一切都重新開始了
It's like it's all brand new.
沃特 沃特 醒醒 醒醒      怎麼了?
Walter. Walter, wake up. Wake up.        Mmm. What?
是亨利 他溜出房間
It's Henry. He snuck out of his room.
又跑到車庫去了
He's down in the garage again by himself.
好吧 告訴他回去睡覺
Well, tell him to come to bed.
我知道 我每晚都這麼和他說
I know. I tell him every night,
但是他得親耳聽到你說
but he needs to hear it from, you know, you.
好吧
Yeah.
我就來
I'm on it.
喲 這麼晚了你要去哪?
Whoa, where are you going this time of night?
我要去告訴那小傢伙讓他停手 我要睡覺
I'm gonna tell the little guy to knock it off so I can sleep.
好吧
Right.
我也要去那 來吧 我們去包抄他
I was going to the same place. Come on. Let's triple-team him.
算了吧 你和你的毛茸茸朋友去吧
That's okay. You've got your little furry friend.
晚安
Good night.
除了球拍 你還在做什麼?
What are you making besides a racket?
你也睡不著嗎?
You couldn't sleep, either?
哦 夥計 事實上 我正睡得香
Well, actually, mate, I was having a brilliant kip
接著就被你的崩崩聲給吵醒了
till you started banging away.
我有個主意
I just had this idea.
哦 什麼? 讓我們明天再想吧
Oh, yeah? Well, let's have the idea in the morning.
就十分鐘 求你了
Just 10 more minutes, please?
十分鐘 好吧
Ten more minutes, all right, yes.
不過以後沒我在身邊不要亂動這些工具
But no more mucking about with tools when I'm not around.
這很危險
It's not safe.
媽媽和你說不要動 你要聽她的話 還有晚上也是
Or when your mother's asked you not to. Or at night.
在廁所 在爬埃弗勒斯峰的時候
Or in a toilet. Or when you're climbing Mount Everest.
還有捏鼻子的時候 同意嗎?
Or picking your nose. Agreed?
同意      那你說吧
Agreed.        There you go.
你能和我說話嗎? 我喜歡聽你說話
Can you talk to me? I like it when you talk.
你想讓我說什麼?
What do you want me to talk about?
隨便 隨便說說
Doesn't matter. Just talk.
你的聲音很好玩
You have a funny voice.
你很容易滿足 不是嗎?
You're quite easily entertained, aren't you?
給你一個小電鋸 一塊木頭 再來一點嘮叨
Give you a buzz saw, a block of wood, and some chatter...
嘿 沃特 你和他說了嗎?
Hey, Walter, did you talk to him?
是啊 一切正常 他會回去睡覺
Yes, and everything's fine. He'll stick to the schedule.
出什麼事了?
What's going on?
我有了新點子 親愛的 現在得立刻投入工作
I've had a breakthrough, love. Got to get to work right away.
現在?
Now?
一刻都不能停
Not a moment to spare!
你簡直是個女神
You're a goddess.
先生 你今天真早啊
Sir? You're in early.
說曹操 曹操到
Just the woman I wanted to see.
看看這個
Have a look at this.
現在 我們得馬上開工
Now, we need to get started on this right away.
是一個海貍?
It's a beaver?
這是未來
It's the future.
就這個?
This?
會說話的木質海貍
The Talking Beaver Woodworking Set.
只要幾個簡單的工具 一塊木頭
You get your basic tools, a block of wood
還有一隻會說話的海貍陪你一起工作
and a talking beaver to work right alongside of you.
親愛的 你該看看那些孩子
You should see the kids, love.
我是說 他們有手機 電腦
I mean, they've got their cell phones and their computers,
但是 你給他們一塊木頭 一個錘子 一把鋸子
but, wow, you give them a block of wood, a hammer and a saw?
我的親娘七舅老爺
Bob's their bleeding auntie.
他們那些可憐的小腦袋可喜歡這些啦
Their poor little brains are starving for something like this.
所以 你想說建一條新的生產線 在聖誕的時候?
So, you're talking about a new product line for what? Christmas?
聖誕? 我說的是現在 女士 今天
Christmas? I'm talking about right now, woman. Today.
就這個上午
This morning.
我覺得應該要有個工具配套市場
I guess there could be an ancillary market in more tools.
還要對木料進行粗加工?
Maybe pre-cut lumber pieces?
有點像樂高玩具 不過都是用木頭做的
Sort of like Lego kits but made of wood.
你可以隨心所欲地把它們拼成各種形狀
And you can work them into shapes on your own.
現在 你也要出謀劃策
Now, that's using your scone.
不只是用木頭做 對嗎? 我們走
Not just made out of wood, is it? Let's go.
但是這就意味著 我是說
But this would mean, I mean,
即使我們及時完成了
even if we could get one ready in time,
這將會是我們展會的唯一展品
this is all we would have for the Expo.
這就是我們所需要的全部 親愛的
That's all we'll need, my darling.
對於那些對一個齧齒動物掌權
And for every person that points out
存在疑議的人來說
that there's a rodent at the helm,
另一個事實提醒著他們
there's another to remind him or her
公司的產量已經提高了35%
that production has already increased by 35%.
一開始的兩周後 沒有人辭職
At the end of those first two weeks, not one person resigns.
一個都沒用
Not one.
現在 我們將要開始...
Now, we're going to start with...
海貍先生 作為核心產品 再加上後續的周邊產品
The Beaver, as a core item, along with endless project kits
可以扭轉局勢
could produce an exponential return.
問題是 我們是要繼續為生存掙扎
The question is, do we want to continue struggling merely to survive,
還是要接受全新 前所未有的嘗試
or do we want to embrace something new, something different,
看看它能給我們帶了什麼?
and see where it takes us?
我們親愛的傑瑞玩具公司又再次
Once again, our beloved Jerry Co.
充滿了美好前程 激情 和活力
Has vision, power, energy, balls.
今天早上三號產品 我們得到了一些製造商的關注
Item number three this morning, we've got some fabrication concerns.
你們在笑什麼
Why are you all laughing?
今天和梅西醫生談話了?
Did you talk to Dr. Macy today?
是啊 他說我恢復得很好
Indeed. He says we're coming along just brilliantly.
他有沒有給你一個時間表
Well, did he give you some kind of a timeline
這個療程何時能結束
for when the treatment might be over?
沒 沒確定 親愛的
No, nothing specific, love.
一周 還是一個月或者...
Like a week, or a month, or...
這得有個過程 親愛的
it's a process, love.
到了合適的時間我們會知道的
We'll know when the time is right.
現在 休息吧 美味的小餡餅
Now, rest up, you delicious little tart.
明天還有很多事
There's more where that came from.
赫克托 我一向說什麼來著 上交之前讀一讀嘛
Hector, what do I always say, man? Read it before you turn it in.
看在老天的份上 這是你的家事
It was about your own family, for Christ's sake.
我以為既然是家事
I just figured since it was personal,
就不會有測試題
there wouldn't be no test questions on it.
但是你奶奶告發了你      是啊 她很是自豪
But your own grandma turned you in.        Yes. She was so proud.
開始講述你寫的那些
Talking about the stuff that you had wrote
她在產房的日子
about her back in the day in D.R.
突然她意識到我對此是不知情的
And then all of a sudden, she could just tell I knew nothing about it.
於是她開始痛哭 打電話給校長說她沒有
So, she starts crying. She calls the principal, says she doesn't...
這事和我沒什麼關係 你明白的 對吧
All right. My name stays out of this. You understand that, right?
她說我撒謊 是個騙子
She called me a liar and a cheater.
好吧 好吧
All right, all right, all right. Look.
我給你搞一個虛假網站 可以了吧
Okay, I'm gonna make a dummy website, all right?
你告訴他們你是自己出的錢 然後論文就到手了
You tell them you sent in your money, you got your paper.
你就知道這些就夠了 行不
That's all you know, okay?
赫克托 我得走了
Hector, look, I gotta go.
明天我就給你網站哈
I'm gonna give you the website tomorrow, all right?
赫克托      好的 好的
Hector!        Yes, yes, yes.
非常好
Great. Good.
諾拉
Norah!
嗨      嗨
Hey.        Hey.
你怎麼汗涔涔的      我剛在做瑜伽
Why are you all sweaty?        I was doing yoga.
真男人啊      下犬式太操蛋了
Manly.        Downward Dog's a bitch.
你今晚忙不忙      你這是約我出去嗎
Are you busy tonight?        Are you asking me out?
不 完全不是
No. Not at all.
我就隨便問一下 如果你忙的話
I was just gonna casually inquire if you're busy
就看不到我花費整晚
without making it seem like I'd been up all night
精心策劃的結晶了
planning something elaborate.
你還花了整晚精心策劃啊
Have you been up all night planning something elaborate?
是啊 我準備了地圖裝備什麼的
Yeah, I have, like, maps and stuff.
你七點來接我吧 十二點前我得回家
You can pick me up at 7:00. I have to be back at 12:00.
太讚了 這就是約會了 是約會吧
Awesome, so it's a date. I mean, it is, right?
拭目以待吧
We'll see.
淡定
Cool.
別搞砸了啊
Don't mess this up.
你讓我來主導 是吧
You let me lead, all right?
你準備好了沒 座位預定在八點
Are you almost ready? Reservation's at 8:00.
該死 女人 看看你的樣子
Bloody hell, woman. Look at you.
你看上去挺帥氣嘛
Well, you're looking pretty good yourself.
你什麼樣沒見過啊      是嘛
Yeah, well, you ain't seen nothing yet.        Yeah?
女孩們為我趕製了很特別的物件
The girls whipped up something special for me.
說的就是小號全套禮服 親愛的
We're talking full-on tux, love.
給我們幾分鐘換個衣服 之後我們出發
Yeah. Just give us a minute to pop it on, and we'll be off.
等一下 這是我們的週年紀念日 親愛的
Wait, it's our anniversary, honey.
所以我才找來禮服啊
That's why I went for the penguin suit.
我不想跟一個玩偶慶祝結婚20週年紀念日
I do not want to celebrate 20 years of marriage with a puppet.
很抱歉 我一直耐著性子也支持你
I'm sorry. I've been very patient and I've been very supportive,
但我想要的是你 不是他
but I want you, not him.
今晚不要
Not tonight.
嗨
Hi.
布萊克 兩位
Black, party of two.
我什麼時候能看一下你的成果
So, when do I get to see some of your pages?
不行 這是個傳銷騙局
Never. it's a pyramid scheme.
我沒告訴過你嗎      沒有
I didn't tell you that?        No.
你沒拿到小冊子麼
You didn't get the brochure?
開玩笑的 我已經搞定了      最好是這樣
I'm kidding. I'll get it done.        You better.
我給你500塊
I'm not giving you 500 bucks
不是讓你買個平板電視放宿舍裡
just so you can buy a flat screen for your dorm room.
我沒有買平板放宿舍裡
I'm not buying a flat screen for my dorm room.
那是什麼
Then, what?
木乃伊      不是木乃伊
A mummy.        No mummy.
那錢要留著買什麼      沒什麼
Then, what? What's it going to?        Nothing.
嗯哼
Mmm-mmm.
你不是那種心血來潮的人
A guy like you doesn't do anything for no reason.
你已經計劃好了
You've got a plan.
我聽了廣播的天氣預報
I was listening to the radio and,
顯然週末會非常熱
apparently, it's gonna be really hot this weekend.
不是熱死人那種 但在均值以上
Not hot-hot, just above average.
你的工作進行得如何      挺順利 很忙
So, how's work?        Good. Yeah, busy.
很忙
Busy?
地圖? 你攢錢就是為了這個?
Maps? That's what you're saving all your money for?
是的
Yeah.
好吧 解釋解釋
Okay, explain,
現在看起來每個紅點都像是藏屍處
because right now, it's looking like where you hide your bodies.
是的 每個紅點都代表一具死屍
It is. Every red dot is a dead body.
我說的是實話
Just trying to be honest.
說正經的 這是幹嘛用的
Okay, really, what's it for?
這上面所有地方
It's, like, all these places
都是物是人非之地
where everything changed in the blink of an eye.
就像馬丁路德金遇刺的陽台
Like the balcony where Martin Luther King got shot.
伍迪·格斯搭乘第一班火車的鐵軌
The train tracks where Woody Guthrie hopped on his first train.
還有呢
And?
我就去參觀這些地方
And I just visit them and
一直到布朗大學開學為止
then I end up at Brown the day before school starts.
算是探尋自我之旅嗎
It's kind of like a find-yourself trip?
不 更像某種告別之旅
No. More like a lose-stuff trip.
你想要告別什麼
What kind of stuff do you want to lose?
最新一次統計是有49樣東西
At last count, 49 things.
一項精心策劃的神秘計劃 有些許古怪
An elaborate, mysterious plan, and a little weird.
但是我喜歡
But I like it.
你的論文報酬發揮作用了
It's your paper-writing dollars at work.
這又是哪出
What was that for?
你說你喜歡出人意料嘛
You said you liked to be surprised.
準備好了麼      幹嘛
Ready?        For what?
這地方不錯
It's a great place.
有點可怕 但是蠻漂亮的
It's kind of scary but beautiful.
我不確定你喜歡什麼顏色 所以我備了各種顏色
Look, I wasn't sure which color you liked, so I kind of got everything.
希望你會喜歡陽光黃
I hope you like sunburst yellow.
珀特 珀特 你要幹啥
Porter? Porter, come on. What are you doing?
很贊是吧
Is this fantastic, or what?
你開什麼玩笑 贊是贊 但我不準備碰它
Are you kidding? it's awesome, but I'm not going to touch it.
為什麼呢      因為所以
Why not?        Because.
啥因為所以 幹嘛不畫      因為我不想畫
Because, what? Why not?        Because I don't want to.
來吧 諾拉 你有畫畫的天賦
Come on, Norah. You have this amazing thing that you do.
你在這裡可以盡情釋放自己
You just put all of yourself out there.
我做圍觀群眾就好
All I can do is sound like other people.
我知道你有話想說      好吧
I know you have something to say.        Okay.
你盡自己最大努力做吧      別介
Knock yourself out. You do it.        Come on.
不 我不會畫
No. I don't paint.
怎麼不會呢 你裝別人可是很在行
Why not? You're so good at being other people.
好吧 也許我能畫畫 但      珀特 畫吧
Well, maybe if I could paint I would, but...        Porter, just start.
好的
Okay.
你要塗什麼 寫諾拉和珀特永結同心?
What are you going to do? Write "Norah + Porter forever"?
那樣會很可愛
Because that'd be pretty cute.
對吧
Right?
這是你一直想要說的話      不
That's what you've been wanting to say.        No.
你寫了400頁的筆記 一個字都沒提到他
You wrote 400 pages of notes. Not one word about him?
我哥哥的事和你沒關係
What happened to my brother is none of your business.
你明白麼
Do you understand?
我以為你有話要說
I just thought there was something you wanted to say
但不知如何開口
and you didn't know how.
這不關你的事
It's none of your business.
什麼樣的人能做出這樣的事來
What kind of person does something like this?
你有毛病麼
What's the matter with you?
繼續拆開吧
Go on. Open it.
亨利幫我做的 基本上就是
Henry helped me, which basically means
我買料 他負責手工
that I bought the wood and he did all the work.
這是個滿載回憶的盒子
It's a memory box.
很精美 謝謝
It's very nice. Thank you.
打開看看
Look inside.
我認為記起我們過去的生活是非常重要的
I thought it was important to remind ourselves of how things were.
生活該是這副模樣
How things should be.
沃特 不不不 沒事了 沒事
Walter. No, no, no. it's okay. it's okay.
這就是你想要的嗎
Is this what you want?
這是療程嗎 老天爺 女人啊
Is this progress? Christ, woman!
他得的是抑鬱癥 不是健忘癥
He's suffering from depression, not amnesia!
你認為問題是出在他忘了過去的生活麼
You think the problem is he can't remember these things?
不 他不能回去 你還不明白麼
No. He can't go back. Don't you see that?
所有的過去都挖掘出來
This is all in the past, and dredging it up...
你知道這條路通向何方麼?
Do you know where this leads?
你知道沃特最終會走哪條路麼?
You know where this Walter goes?
站在十樓的陽台上 脖子一端還綁在浴簾桿上
To a 10th floor balcony, tied to a shower curtain rod.
這是你想要的嗎
Is that what you want?
你想要餘生都和今晚一樣嗎
You want the rest of your life to be just like tonight?
那就是沃特      不 沃特 來
Well, that was Walter.        No, Walter. No, come on.
看看這些 你好好看看
Look at this. You really look at this.
那是你 沃特
That's you, Walter.
記得嗎
Remember that?
那時珀特剛出生 還那麼小
When Porter was born, and he was so little?
醫生把他從我身上拉出來 你就站在他身旁
And they pulled him out of me, and you stood right by him.
你直視他的雙眼
You looked him right in the eye,
你讓他知道你哪裡都不會去
and you let him know that you weren't going anywhere,
你就在他身邊 所以他不會感到害怕
that you were staying right there so he wouldn't be scared.
沃特 這才是你 這才是我愛著的 我需要的人
Walter, that's you. That's the man I love. That's the man I need.
這樣的你還在你的體內 親愛的
You're still inside there, honey.
我知道你在的 我們能回到過去
I know you're in there. We can go back.
我們能過回以前的生活
We can get back to the way that we used to be.
我們不會再一次踏上同樣的路途了 梅勒迪斯
We are not going down that street again, Meredith.
這個人已經走到頭了 他消失了 他必須消失
This man is a dead end. He's gone. He has to be.
你明白麼
You get it?
我為你爭取過
I fought for you.
你沒法下床那兩年
I practically breathed for you for two years
我一直在你身邊
when you couldn't even get out of bed,
我會繼續為你爭取 因為我愛你
and I will continue to fight for you because I love you.
我得知道你會回來 求你回來吧
I've got to know that you're coming back. Come back to me, please.
沃特
Walter?
諾拉 再來一次我可真承受不起
Norah, I can't take this again.
走吧
Come on.
你好 我們一接到消息就趕過來了
Hello. We came as soon as we heard.
我是海貍先生 這位是珀特的父親 沃特
I'm the Beaver, and this is Porter's dad, Walter.
我們會處理的
Listen, we'll get it all sorted.
我已經來了就會處理好一切
I'm here now so we'll take care of things.
開車注意安全
Have a nice safe drive home.
等一下
Wait.
珀特 慢點 我們談談
Porter, mate, hang about. Come on. We can discuss this. Come on.
把那個玩偶給我      冷靜
Give me that thing!        Calm down!
給我 天殺的      住手
Give it to me! Goddamn it!        Stop it!
給我      住手
Give me that thing!        Stop!
別管他
Leave him alone!
珀特 珀特 天啊你沒事吧 沒傷著吧
Porter! Porter! Oh, my God. Porter, are you okay? Are you all right?
珀特 我看看你的手 流血了嗎
Porter, let me see your hands. Are they bleeding?
抱歉 兒子 我不是有意的
I'm sorry, son. I didn't mean to do that.
你別碰他
You keep your hands off him!
珀特 來 讓媽媽看看
Porter, come on. Let me see.
你現在開心了
Are you happy now?
珀特 珀特
Porter? Porter?
現在是五月的聖誕節
It's Christmas in May.
一些零售商如是說
That's what some retailers are saying
海貍先生的伐木工具箱正陸續售罄
with Mr. Beaver Woodchopper Kits selling out in droves.
近來 傑瑞公司一直飽受訂單劇減的困擾
Recently, Jerry Co. had been in steep decline,
今年頭幾個月一直徘徊在破產邊緣
hovering on the verge of bankruptcy earlier this year.
但是有了海貍先生 一時半時是不會破產了
But thanks to Mr. Beaver, that won't be happening any time soon.
這像是免費做了一百萬的廣告啊
It's like a $100 million ad campaign, for free!
傑瑞公司又重回業界 你爸爸會很自豪的
Jerry Co. 's back in the game. The old man would be so proud.
我得把公司交由你接管
I've got to hand it to you.
你在幕後操縱 然後就看我們的成績
You pulled all the strings, and look where we landed.
會再一次登頂
On top, for once.
這很有成就感 不是麼      他們
It feels good, doesn't it?        They.
先生
Sir?
我的家人
My family.
現在我們手頭的採訪請求中誰來頭最大
Who's the biggest interview request we've had so far?
所有的早間新聞
All the morning shows.
CNN CNBC...      今日新聞 去安排吧
CNN, CNBC...        Today Show, then. Set it up.
但是今日新聞已經在播了
But, sir, the Today Show is on television.
我們在遮掩什麼 我們是贏家哎
What are we hiding? We're winners.
應該站在屋頂向全世界呼喊
We should be shouting it from the rooftops.
這肯定會成為一段佳話
It would certainly be a story.
我跟你說個事 其他人我從不告訴
I'm gonna tell you something that I've never told anyone else,
但我想你是準備好了的
but I think you're ready to hear it.
好的
Okay.
我不是玩偶
I'm not a puppet.
我是真實的
I'm real.
活生生的
I'm alive.
世人需要知道這一點
And the world needs to know.
你沒事吧親愛的
You all right, love?
有麻煩嗎
Some trouble?
我今天和梅西醫生談過
I talked to Dr. Macy today.
他又為自己辯解什麼
What did he have to say for himself?
他說你已經有一年多沒去看過他
He says that you haven't been to see him in over a year.
梅西醫生說你病了 沃特 你病得很重
Dr. Macy says that you're sick, Walter. Very sick.
是啊 沒錯
Yeah. Right.
他說這有點狂躁癥的意思
He said this sounds like some kind of a mania.
誰他媽關心梅西醫生說了什麼
Okay, well, who gives a shit what Dr. Macy has to say?
我治好了他
I fixed him.
其他人似乎都接受了
Everybody else seems to get it.
亨利 同事 除了你之外
Henry, people at work. Everyone except you.
這還不能說明什麼嗎
Does that tell you something?
你想永遠這麼活下去嗎 通過手來交談
You just want to live like this forever? Talking through your hand?
我敢說至今為止是前所未有的大成功 不是嗎
I'd say it's been a pretty smashing success so far, wouldn't you?
你需要幫助 沃特 你需要幫助 你病了
You need help, Walter! You need help! You're sick.
幫助 吃藥 讀書 看專家
"Help. " Eat the pill, read the book, see the bleeding expert.
沃特最終還是要自救
Walter finally helped himself
聽聽你說的話 你瘋了
Listen to yourself. This is insane.
你在和一個玩偶講話
You're talking about a puppet.
不 梅勒迪斯 是你在和玩偶講話
No, Meredith. You're talking about a bloody puppet.
我們談論的是一個奇跡
We're talking about a miracle.
我們是誰 沃特
Who's "we," Walter?
我知道這很艱難 同伴 我知道
I know it's hard, mate. I know.
你不能搞混了
You can't afford to get mixed up in all of this.
你要繼續前進 勇往直前不要回頭
You just keep moving. Keep moving and don't look back.
你說的沒錯
You're right, of course.
沃特病了
Walter is sick.
但是有一點不要搞錯 親愛的 我哪裡都不會去
But make no mistake about it, love. I'm not going anywhere.
我已經租好了房子
I've rented a house.
兒子 還有能帶的我都要帶過去
I'm taking the boys and everything we can carry.
我不想你打電話來 也不想看到你過去串門
I don't want you to call. I don't want you to visit.
如果你決定要丟棄自己 我是沒法阻止你
If you're determined to lose your mind, well, I can't stop you.
但是我不會放任兒子們眼睜睜看你發瘋
But I'm not gonna let them stand there and watch it. Not my sons.
在單位你瘋一瘋可以
Insanity may play at the office,
但是在法官面前可不起作用
but it's not gonna work in front of a judge.
為什麼你不跟我們一起走啊
Why aren't you coming with us?
下次吧 夥伴 下一次吧
Another time, mate. Another time.
可我想跟你在一起
But I want to stay with you.
你先跟媽媽走好麼 這問題我們會處理好 看著吧
You go with your mum, all right? We'll get it sorted. You'll see.
很快一切就又會好起來的
Everything will be good again real soon. All right.
拜拜      走吧
Bye.        Let's go.
拜拜
Bye.
我愛你 爸爸
I love you, Daddy.
我也愛你 兒子 我也愛你
I love you, too, son. I love you, too.
去吧 你該走了 去吧
Go on. Off you go. Go on.
有時 麥特啊 我能叫你麥特嗎
Well, sometimes, Matt... May I call you Matt?
當然可以
Yeah, sure.
有時 在半夜的時候
Sometimes, a single inspiration just comes to you
你靈光一現
in the middle of the night.
但是你的天賦似乎隱藏在手套玩偶背後
But your genius seems to hide in a stuffed toy.
所以人們不得不懷疑你精神有點毛病
So people have to doubt your sanity a little.
哎 莫扎特有時候還學貓叫呢
Well, Mozart was said to occasionally meow like a cat,
但是他的音樂事業一帆風順
but he got on all right.
他的音樂還是很偉大 你不這樣認為麼
Great music, don't you think?
沃特 我想談一下抑鬱癥
Walter, I want to talk about depression.
因為據我得到的消息
Because the way it's been told to me,
你開始用玩偶交談
this whole thing started as a way for you
完全是為了治療心理疾病
to deal with your mental illness.
好吧
Well, all right.
麥特 有時候
Well, sometimes, Matt,
我們到達一定高度之後 為了繼續前進
we reach a point where, in order to go on,
就不得不將過去的記錄抹去
we have to wipe the slate clean.
我們要將自身視為一個盒子並置身其中
We start to see ourselves as a box that we're trapped inside.
無論我們怎樣嘗試逃脫出來
And no matter how we try and escape,
自救 看心理醫生 嗑藥
self-help, therapy, drugs,
我們只會越陷越深
we just sink further and further down.
只有一種方式才能真正地突破牢籠
The only way to truly break out of the box
就是捨棄所有
is just to get rid of it altogether.
我是說 你起初所鑄造的輝煌
I mean, you built it in the first place.
如果你身邊的人都從精神上打擊你 輝煌又有何用
If the people around you are breaking your spirit, who needs them?
老婆假裝愛你
Your wife who pretends to love you,
兒子忍受不了你
your son who can't even stand you.
我說 把他們的苦逼置於腦後吧
I mean, put them out of their misery.
重新開始不可怕
Starting over isn't crazy.
可怕的是日復一日
Crazy is being miserable
變得苦逼 夢遊樣四處轉
and walking around half asleep, numb,
麻木不仁
day after day after day.
可怕的是假裝開心
Crazy is pretending to be happy.
自己悲慘的餘生
Pretending that the way things are
都不得不一直維持假裝的狀態生活
is the way they have to be for the rest of your bleeding life.
所有潛在的希望
All the potential, hope,
所有的愉悅 感受
all that joy, feeling,
所有生活從你身上榨取的激情
all that passion that life has sucked out of you.
伸出手 抓住它
Reach out, grab a hold of it
然後從吸血的暴民手中奪回來
and snatch it back from that blood-sucking rabble.
沃特 很高興你來接受採訪
Walter, it's good to have you here.
謝謝
Thank you.
這就是沃特.布萊克現在的寫照
This is a picture of Walter Black,
一個絕望 沮喪的人
a hopelessly depressed individual
他變身海貍先生
who becomes the Beaver,
引發了一種風潮
who becomes a phenomenon.
有很多人都非常渴望收聽
There's a lot of people out there who are desperate enough to listen.
人們似乎都擁有
People seem to love a train wreck
一種葉公好龍的心理
when it's not happening to them.
諾拉 我們談談嘛
Norah, look, we need to talk.
現在不是好時機
Now's not a good time.
是啊 我給你打過電話 發過短信 還Q過你
Yeah, well, I called you, I texted you, and I IM'd you,
從沒有時機對過的時候 所以
and it never seems like a good time. So...
也許你該把這當成是一種暗示
Maybe you should take that as a hint.
我是傻子 可以了吧 我也不想事情發展成這樣
I'm an idiot, all right? That's not how I wanted things to turn out.
我喜歡你 好吧 我確實很在乎
I like you, all right? I actually give a shit.
你不用在乎我 你甚至不瞭解我
You don't give a shit about me. You don't even know me.
你哥哥死於吸毒過量 對吧
Look, your brother OD'd, all right?
但是放棄自己的天賦 你成為現在這樣
But ditching your own talent, what makes you you,
這也不會讓他起死回生 只會讓你一事無成
that's not gonna bring him back. It's just going to make you nothing.
你他媽離我遠點
You stay the hell away from me.
你和你一家的精神病
You and your psycho family.
你開心嗎 你發自肺腑地開心嗎
Are you happy? Are you truly, truly happy?
約翰 我們身上都缺少一樣東西
Because, Jon, there's something lacking in all of us.
缺失了一塊
A missing piece.
有一小塊黑點或是暗點
There's a little bit of a black spot or a dark spot.
明顯嗎
It's that obvious?
約翰 很抱歉這樣說 但沃特需要一些幫助
I'm sorry to say, Jon, but Walter needs a little help.
因為他現在無法流利地表達出來
Because he's not too articulate at the moment.
事實上 他的狀態很不好
In fact, he's not well.
起床 起床
Get up. Get up.
起來 你這個悲催的傢伙
Get up, you miserable wanker.
你不會從沃特口中挖到太多話的
You're not going to get much out of ol' Walter.
他有些感覺不適 瞭解沒
He's feeling a bit under the weather, you see?
來吧 廣播節目而已
Come on. it's a radio show.
人們又看不到玩偶
People can't even see the puppet.
為什麼要通過玩偶講話呢
So why talk through the puppet?
(相似點)
(咬嘴唇)
(按摩眉毛)
(憎恨父親 代代如此)
你好
Hello?
小梅 是我
Mere, it's me.
沃特 你沒事吧
Walter, are you okay?
嗯 我說
Yeah, look,
我不能 我不能
I can't I can't
你在幹什麼
What are you doing?
發生了什麼事
What's going on?
沃特 沃特 講話啊
Walter? Walter, talk to me!
你在和誰講電話
Who are you talking to?
掛掉 現在就掛掉      沃特
Hang up. You hang up right now.        Walter?
你媽會縫合吧
Can your mother stitch?
你永遠都贏不了
You'll never win.
我想要爸爸 爸爸在哪      我知道
I want Daddy. Where's Daddy?        I know.
我想要海貍先生
I want the Beaver.
還沒睡呢 親愛的 你去找你爸行麼
Are you awake? Honey, you've got to go get Dad, all right?
為啥
Why?
他不接電話 亨利也哭個不停
He's not answering his phone, and Henry won't stop crying.
我都不知道怎麼辦是好 求你了
I just don't know what to do. Please.
來 寶貝 我們一會就去找爸爸 不哭了啊
Come on, baby. We're going to find Daddy soon. it's okay.
我沒有給你你想要的東西嗎
Haven't I given you exactly what you asked for?
你不需要家人 沃特
You don't need them, Walter.
我愛你
I love you.
我才是那個深深 深深愛著你的人
I'm the only one that really, really loves you.
所以我才不會讓你回到以前的生活
And that is why I would never let you go back.
永遠不會
Never.
我不想睡覺了
I don't want to sleep anymore.
也許
Maybe...
也許我們該做點什麼
Maybe, you know, we should work on something.
好的 同伴 來吧
Yeah, sure, mate. Come on.
沃特 不要這樣
Walter, not like this.
不要這樣
Don't do it.
情況會比以往糟糕 要糟糕得多
It will be worse than before. Much worse.
你最後想變成一坨孤零零 毫無價值的屎嗎
Do you want to end up a worthless, lonely piece of shit?
沒有我你就是個廢物 沃特
You're nothing without me, Walter.
廢物
Nothing!
我只是你的一部分
I'm the only part of you that works.
很抱歉
I'm sorry.
沃特 你還記得你的兒子亨利嗎
Walter! How about Henry, your kid? You remember him?
沃特
Walter!
爸爸
Dad?
血壓正在下降 等上了手術台再動止血帶
BP's dropping. Don't touch the tourniquet until he's on the table.
這是他還有脈搏的原因
It's the only reason he still has a pulse.
醒來
Wake
*從睡夢中醒來*
*From your sleep*
*擦乾眼淚*
*The drying of your tears*
*我們逃離了當下*
*Today we escape*
作為傑瑞公司的新CEO
As the new CEO of Jerry Co. ,
我向大家保證公司已經交由可靠之人管理
I want to assure people that the company is back in good hands.
*收好行囊*
*Pack*
*整好衣裳*
*And get dressed*
*在你父親聽到我們之前*
*Before your father hears us*
*在*
*Before*
*地獄之門*
*All hell*
*開啟之前*
*Breaks loose*
我給了珀特200塊
I paid Porter $200,
他去做了調查
and he did some research.
我辜負了家人的期望
I let my family down.
我對此感到非常慚愧
I'm really ashamed about this,
我想讓這件事盡快過去
and I just want to put it behind me as soon as possible.
尊敬的珀特 布朗大學招生辦很遺憾地通知你
由於近來的一些事宜 你的大學錄取被取消
請來年再申
孩子 你在蓮花池裡釣魚嗎
Grasshopper, are you fishing in our lily pond?
走吧 咱去探望下你爸爸
Come on. Let's go see your dad.
我不去      好吧
I'm not going.        Fine.
如果你不想去就不去
If you don't want to go, then don't go.
但你也不能成天睡覺啊
But you're not just going to sleep all day.
來吧
Come on.
來 珀特 起來 咱們走
Come on, Porter. Let's go. Get up!
看在上帝的份上      住手
For Christ's sake.        Stop!
我們走嗎      別動我
Are we going?        Stop! Stop!
好的
Yes.
隨你了
Fine.
找點事做 行嗎
Just do something, all right?
出去散個步 偷輛車 我都不管
Go outside, take a walk, steal a car. I don't care.
我回家時不想看到你還躺在床上
I just don't want to find you back in bed when I get home.
你的家人來了
Your family's here.
沒事的 去吧
It's okay. Go on.
嗨 小傢伙 你好嗎
Hey, little fella. How are you?
好
Good.
這是什麼呀
What's that?
這是個腦子      哇 是腦子呢
it's a brain.        Wow. it's a brain!
媽媽說你的大腦壞掉了
Mom says yours got broken.
這個正能派上用場
This will come in handy.
這麼說 你瘋了嗎
So, are you crazy?
也許吧
Maybe.
我們正在這治療
We're working on it.
這意味著你能回家嗎
Does that mean you can come home?
這一點我們也正在努力
We're working on that, too.
你哥哥呢
Hey, where's your brother?
可能在睡覺 他一直在睡覺
Probably sleeping. It's all he does.
過來
Come here.
過來 我要咬你的耳朵
Come here! I'll bite you on your ear!
(睡覺)
(這兒見 拜託!)
喔
Wow.
我給你發了15條短信
I must have sent you 15 texts.
我都放棄了
I'd given up on you.
彼此彼此吧
Well, that makes two of us.
你說得對 我的確是想要傾訴
You were right. I guess I had some stuff to say.
顯然 有很多東西想要表達
Apparently, a lot of stuff.
不管怎樣 你現在知道我的想法
Anyway, now you know what's on my mind,
這樣就可以寫演講稿了
so you can write my speech.
不行
No.
我想我已經正式退出代寫這一行了
I think I'm officially out of that business.
你還欠我一篇演講稿
You owe me.
這是你為我畫的
You made this for me.
昨天畫的
Yesterday.
為什麼呢
How come?
因為牆上的內容遠遠要多於
Because there's more that belongs on a wall than,
"諾拉有個死鬼哥哥"
"Norah has a dead brother. "
即使是一團亂
Even if it is a big mess.
畫得很好啊
It's amazing.
有意思 我覺得畫了坨屎 你覺得畫得很好
Funny. I think it's a mess, and you think it's amazing.
我覺得你很棒 你卻覺得自己什麼都不是
And I think you're amazing, and you think you're a mess.
你知道麼 我不想再思考了
You know what? I don't want to think anymore.
你仍欠我一篇演講稿
You still owe me a speech.
一定要保證像我的口氣
Just make sure it sounds like me.
那麼我是坐這寫然後再被逮捕一次呢
So, do I just sit here writing and get arrested again?
不用 你拿走吧 笨蛋
No, take it with you, dummy.
我拿走?
Take it with me?
畢業生們 死去的詩人們
Good afternoon, graduates, dead poets,
畫家們 未來的愛因斯坦們 下午好
painters, future Einsteins, and all those in between.
今天我站在這裡 警告大家有人在對你們說謊
Today I'm here to warn you that you are being lied to.
父母 老師 醫生都對我們撒了謊
Our parents, our teachers, our doctors have lied to us.
說的都是同一句謊言 就6個字
And it's the exact same lie. The same six words,
"一切都會好的"
"Everything is going to be okay. "
但要是好不了呢
But what if it isn't?
要是有些體驗是遺傳來的
What if some of human experience is just something you inherit,
就像卷髮或是碧眼一樣
like curly hair or blue eyes?
要是你生來就痛苦 生來就是一樁悲劇呢
What if pain is just in your DNA and tragedy is your birthright?
又或者
Or what if..
或者有時      有時
"Or what if sometimes... "        ... sometimes...
...突然之間 它成了你的最低期望
"... right out of the blue, when you least expect it,
破事就發生了呢
"shit just happens?
"Shit just happens. "
好吧 我保證 現在大家都在想
Okay, I'm sure, right now, you're all thinking,
靠 這是我聽過的最黑暗的畢業生演講
"Man, this is the darkest graduation speech I've ever heard. "
是的 我同意你們的意見 但這不是我寫的
And it is. I agree with you, but I didn't write it.
我花了很長時間等待謊言成真
I've spent so much time waiting for this lie to come true
所以我付錢讓別人來替我說出真相
that I finally paid someone to tell the truth for me.
我並不好
I'm not okay.
一點都不好
Not at all.
真相是
The truth is,
我缺失了一樣東西
I'm missing something,
是我的最愛
the thing I loved the most,
是一張我希望他就在前排坐著的面龐
the face I wish were in the front row right now.
我永遠都回不來的哥哥
The brother I'll never get back.
那麼我該怎麼做
So what do I do with that?
我們大家會怎麼做
What do any of us do,
除了說謊以外
besides lie?
我相信的是
This is what I believe.
現在禮堂裡 有人正與你一起
Right now, in this auditorium, there is someone who is with you.
他願意來接你 彈去你身上的灰塵
Someone who is willing to pick you up, dust you off,
親吻你 原諒你
kiss you, forgive you,
容忍你 等著你 陪著你
put up with you, wait for you, carry you,
愛著你
love you.
雖然事事不會一直都順利
So, while everything may not always be okay,
但有一點我相信是真的
one thing I know is true.
你沒有必要一個人戰鬥
You do not have to be alone.
我沒想到你會來
I didn't think you'd come.
我也沒想到自己會來
I didn't think I would, either.
我很高興你還活著
I'm just glad you're still here.
我身體的大部分是還活著
Yeah, most of me, anyway.
嗯
Yeah.
你知道嗎 我還是個孩子的時候
You know, when I was a little kid,
我滿心期望就是像你一樣
man, all I ever wanted was to be like you.
之後我長大了
Then I got older,
我又想成為別人
and I just wanted to be anybody else.
現在呢
And now?
爸爸
Dad.
這是沃特·布萊克現在的寫照
This is a picture of Walter Black,
他曾不得不成為海貍先生
who had to become a beaver,
也不得不為人父
who had to become a father,
因此有朝一日
so that, one day,
這可能正是沃特·布萊克一生的寫照
this might just be a picture of Walter Black.